A journey from which you can never return.
二度と戻れない旅
Treasures that you can never again acquire.
二度と手に入らない宝物
Your very life, which once lost will never be restored.
二度と帰らない生命
Nearly all things in this world
will never go back to the way they once were.
この世にあるもののほとんどが二度と元には戻らない
Understanding that,
それが分かっていながら 人は今日も一歩前へと進む
people still continue, even today,
to get up and take another step forward.
Spurred on by the thought of viewing
a landscape they've never seen before,
一度も見だことのない景色を見る為に 歩き続ける
they keep on walking...
道への憧れは 誰にも止められない
A longing for the unknown, you see,
is something not a single soul is capable of stopping.
In any case, that was pretty amazing, Nanachi!
それにしてもすごかったぞ ナナチ
Using the opponent's own special ability against it
like that was a brilliant strategy!
敵の能力を逆手にとっだ素晴らしい作戦だ
I wish you'd come with us
to the bottom of the netherworld!
君も奈落の底に付いて来てくれればいいのに
W-well, actually...
あ あのな
I have something to ask of you...
お前に頼みたいこができた
Oh! What is it?!
おぉ なんだ 何でも言ってくれ
You can ask anything of me!
Well...
I knew it would be, but it truly is a hard thing to ask...
さすがに言いずれーんだけどな
Don't hold back!
遠慮はするな
Alright, here it goes.
じゃあ 頼む
'Kay.
Please kill Mitty for me.
ミーティを 殺してくれ
Huh?
Everyone, unable to resist, goes down in
誰もが逆らえずに潜っていく
その目を灯火より輝かせて
Make those eyes shine brighter than a torch
The destination we are aiming for is deep
目指す先は深く まっすぐに迷い込む
We squarely lose our way
The trap of the open-mouthed netherworld
口開けた奈落の罠 真実の跡を追いかけよう
Let's chase the traces of truth
If an answer can be found now, we don't mind losing it all
今荅えが 見つかるなら 全部失くしてもいい
The echo is still reverberating
その声を 離さないように 木霊がまだ響いてる
So that we do not part with that voice
羅針盤はずっと 闇を指したまま逃げ場のない 方へ
The compass is always
Pointed to the darkness
Where there is no escape
In that direction
Even if that is a curse
それが呪いでも 鼓動は本物
The pulse is the real thing
Never again will the yearning stop
二度と憧れは 止まらない
The Challengers
What was that all of a sudden?
何なんだよ急に 「二時間だけ眠る」って
He was like, "I'm gonna sleep - just for two hours."
His belly button looks like it hurts,
but it doesn't appear he's been poisoned.
へそは痛そうになってるけど
毒は通ってねぇしな
I suppose...
やっぱ あれぶっぱなしたせいだよな
he must be like this 'cause he fired that thing.
Finally...
ようやく ようやく見つけたよ ミーティ
Finally I have found it...
Mitty.
How nice it would be...
いいな
God...
神様
if that's the bottom of this world, I...
同じ地の底なら オイラここに行きたいです
would like to go there.
God...
神様
Hey! Let's hurry over there!
ほら 早く行こうぜ
You stink... Don't stand so close to me!
くせーな 少し離れろよ
「アビス」」の探窟家だってよ
I hear he's a cave raider from the Abyss.
What's he doing in a place like this?
なんでこんなとこに
Now, I believe it is time for a new approach
that's free from the influence of conventional wisdom.
今や 常識に左右されない
新しいアプローチが試されるべきと考えます
From the chief territory of the far north, Sereny...
極北の要であるセレニの地
I've come here...
私はここに奈落に次世代を切り開くにふさわしい子供たちを見つけに来ました
in search of children suitable
for forging a path to the netherworld's next era.
I am Bondrewd.
私はボンドルド
I'm a cave raider of the Abyss and a White Whistle.
奈落の探窟家 「白笛」です
Brave children, who do not falter even at the prospect
of setting foot inside the chasm...
深淵に踏み入ることも厭わない 勇気ある子供達
please, take a step forward.
どうぞ 一歩前へ
I'm really here now...
ほんとに 来ちまった
You're so annoying!
うっせぇなぁ
Get outta here!
あっち行けっ
Hey, let's give it a shot...
ねぇやろうよ
I don't keep company with idiots.
アホは相手にしねーよ
Let's go.
行こうぜ
Ah... O-okay...
オイラ達の他にもいるのか
So we're not the only ones, then, huh?
さぁ皆さん蘢にお乗りください
Now, everyone, come and board the vessel.
Fear not, for my team of cave raiders
will escort you throughout the journey.
ご安心ください 道中は 全て私の探窟隊が護衛致します
Your destination is at a depth of around 13,000 meters.
目的地は 深度約一万三千メートル
There, in the depths' fifth layer, the Sea of Corpses,
深界五層「なきがらの海」
lies the netherworld's forward operating base,
世界最後の謎に挑む 奈落の前線基地です
where we strive to unravel
the final mysteries of this world.
This tastes so bland...
味がしない
Hey, you!
ねぇ君
What do you want to be?
君は何になりたい やっぱ白笛
A White Whistle, right?!
Hey, what's this all about?
んなぁ 何だよぉ
Being a White Whistle sure would be great, huh?!
なりたいよね白笛
Don't you think we've got ourselves
an amazing chance here?
これって すっごいチゃンスだと思わない
I-I was fine with whatever
as long as I could come here.
お オイラは ここに来れれば何でも良かったんだ
Before coming here, I'd go to garbage dumps
and pick out the least disgusting stuff to eat.
ここに来る前は ゴミ溜めからマシなゴミを拾って食べてた
Everyone else resorted to stealing or
begging while singing songs on the streets...
皆は盗みとか 歌うたって物乞いとかしてたけど
オイラは それ以外に能がなくてよ
But I... didn't have the talent for anything else...
That's a great skill to have!
その特技 いいじゃん
Huh?
There's nothing but treasures to pick up down here!
ここなら拾う物全部お宝だよ
Okay...
Hey, hey, if you're fine with whatever,
then be my partner!
ねぇねぇなんでもいいなら あたしの相棒になってよ
Uh...
あたしミーティ 未来の白苗だよ
I'm Mitty! A future White Whistle!
Hey, what's your name?
ねぇ君は
I-I'm Nanachi.
な ナナチだ
Yippee! Nanachi!
ナナチ よろしくね
Nice to meet you!
Shh! Shh!
Oh?
It says, "Capital of the Unreturned."
「帰らずの都」って書いてある
奈落文字読めるの
You can read nether glyphs?
The only books found in the garbage
are the ones other people can't read, you see...
ゴミの中で余るのは 他の連中が読めない本だからな
The way to pronounce nether glyphs has been lost,
奈落文字は発音が失われてるから
so pronunciations from our official language
are used in their place.
公用語あてて使われてんだ
It's simple once you get the hang of it.
覚えりゃ簡単だよ
そうなの 教えてよ
Really? Teach me!
鳥かな
I wonder if that was a bird.
Next time, let's go check it out together!
今度一緒に見に行こ
O-okay...
Wow!
Please be careful...
気をつけてください
If you climb more than 10 meters,
you'll be hit with the strains of ascending.
10メートル以上昇ると 上昇負荷がかかります
Huh?
Nanachi, come with me!
ナナチ来て
Whoa...
It's beautiful...
綺麗
It'll be alright!
大丈夫だよ
Y-yeah...
Now, everyone, let me show you to your room.
さぁ皆さん お部屋に行きましょう
Hey, so what's the Abyssal Faith?
ねぇねえ「アビス信仰」って何
Hmm... To put in a nutshell...
かいつまんでいうと
When a life is lost in the Abyss,
the soul is said to return to the bottom of this planet,
アビスで命を落としたら 魂が星の底に帰って
and then the soul changes form and departs
on a journey to someone who has wished for life...
命を願った者のところへ形を変えて旅に出る って感じのだな
Or something like that...
This very pit, the bottom of which
is still unknown, replaces God.
今だ底知れぬこの穴を神様の代わりにした
Well, I suppose it's just kind of a source of comfort
and support that cave raiders rely on.
ま 探窟家達の心の拠り所みたいなもんだ
Wow...
ナナチ まじすごいね
Nanachi, you're pretty amazing!
That's my partner for you!
You're the brains of our team!
さすが あたしの相棒だね プレインだね
Hmm, I guess...
まぁな
And you're good at drawing, too!
絵も上手だし
Ilim...
イリム さぁ来てください
please come over here.
Okay!
はい
This time it's Ilim's turn, huh?
今度はイリムか
I hope I get to go out there soon, too...
オイラも早く外出てぇな
There are certainly a lot fewer of us here now...
もう随分 少なくなっちゃったしね
In any case, it'd be great if the two of us
are able to go out there together!
どうせだったら 二人で一緒に出られるといいね
Yeah, I guess...
まぁな
ミーティ ミーティ
Mitty...
Mitty.
ミーティ
Now, please come with me.
さぁ 一緒に来てください
Okay...
ふぁぁい
今日は健康診断の後 少し外を歩きましょう
After today's medical checkup,
let's go on a little walk outside.
Bondrewd, take me, too...
ボントルド オイラも
Just wait your turn, Nanachi.
No need to be impatient.
順番ですよ ナナチ 慌てないで
Mitty...
ミーティ
Sovereign of Dawn!
What in the world are you thinking?!
黎明卿 何を考えているんですか
Bringing so many people
down to the fifth layer like this...
あの数の人間を五層に それも海外の子供達まで
Even children from overseas...
Why bring this up only now?
今更どうしたのです
It is also for this very purpose that I advocated
to have Black Whistles enter the fifth layer.
黒笛の五層立ち入りを進言したのも この為ですよ
Well, it'd be different if they were cave raiders,
しかし探窟家ならともかく 負荷的に二度と戻れない子供達はその
but taking children, who'll never be able to return
given the strain of doing so, is simply...
from a humane perspective...
人道的に
Ah, then there is no need to worry.
ああ なら心配ありませんよ
For I am not making use of them as humans, you see...
あれらは人間としての運用はしておりませんので
Care to have a look?
ご覧になります
Mitty...
ミーティ
Mitty!
MITTY!
ミーティ
N-Nanachi...
な ナナチ
M-Mitty...
ミ ミーティ
My, my.
What perfect timing...
ちょうどよかった
Nanachi.
ナナチ さあ 順番ですよ
Come, it is your turn now.
That elevator is capable of quickly going
to the depths' sixth layer just below us.
あの昇降機は すぐ下の深界六層に行けるんですよ
Although its destination is no more than a dead end...
降りた先は袋小路なんですが
色々と試すのに丁度いい深さでしてね
it is just the perfect depth for testing out
a number of things, you see...
It's my own miniature garden.
私の箱庭なんです
六層の呪い 「死か 人間性を失うか」
The sixth layer's Curse:
"Death, or loss of one's humanity"...
I'd sure like to do something about it.
なんとかしたいですよね
Those chambers you are in
are capable of forcing the Curse all to one side.
あなた方が入ってるそれ
呪いを片側に押し付ける事が出来るんですよ
人とそれ以外では 上手くいかなかったんですが
Attempts were made that paired a person with something
besides a fellow human, but they didn't go well...
However, Nanachi just happened to come join us...
丁度ナナチも来てくれた事です
I regret having to use two cute,
little beings such as yourselves...
可愛らしい生体を二つも使うのは 惜しいですが
But, as you two are such close friends,
I'm sure this will be a success.
二人共仲良しです きっと成功しますよ
So you're saying... you tricked us?
あたし達を 騙してたの
Heavens no.
とんでもない
The result of this research will give birth to the hint
needed to drive the darkness from this chasm.
この研究の果てに 深淵の闇を払うヒントが生まれるのです
あなた方のお陰ですよ
It will be thanks to all of you...
Mitty, you will be on the side to which the Curse is driven.
ミーティ あなたは押し付けられる側です
なるベく耐えてくださいね
Please do your best to endure it, okay?
Mitty!
ミーティ
If you die partway through,
your partner will also be hit with the Curse.
途中で死んだら 相棒も呪いにかかってしまいます
Nanachi...
ナナチ
Well then, let's get started.
では 始めましょうか
Nanachi!
ナナチ
It's alright. It's alright...
大丈夫 大丈夫だよ
I'll endure this...
あたしが耐えるから だから あたしが人間じゃなくなっちゃったら
So, if I end up not being human anymore...
Please...
お願い
let my soul return to you, Nanachi!
またナナチのところに 魂が帰るように
MITTY!
ミーティ
NO!
It hurts!
痛い
痛い痛い
It hurts! It hurts so bad!
God... please save us.
I... finally found it.
オイラ ようやく見つけたんです 宝物を見つけたんです
ミーティ ミーティ
Mitty! Mitty!
I... finally found it.
I found a treasure I hold dear...
Ow!
Please...
どうか どうか奪わないで
いた
Please don't take her away from me.
ころ ころして ころして
Kill... Kill me...
Kill me...
PLEASE!
お願い
Oh...
My, my, how very interesting.
これはこれは興味深い
Wonderful...
すばらしい
The two of you are truly wonderful...
二人共実にすばらしい
Nanachi...
ナナチ ナナチ
Just as usual, I see you're drawing
instead of helping with the research...
相変わらず 研究も手伝わずにお絵描きですか
You sure are cute...
君はかわいいですね
Oh, right...
そうそう ミーティが受けた「呪い」がわかりましたよ
I now understand the "curse" that Mitty received.
It's quite a wonderful result.
すばらしい結果です
For it to produce such a byproduct,
the Abyss truly is astonishing.
あのような副産物が得られるとは
やはりアビスは驚異的です
The Curse, which she received twofold,
did not just cause the loss of her humanity...
二度とに受けた「呪い」が彼女にもたらしたものは
「人間性の喪失」だけではなく
but also made her incapable of dying.
「死ねなくなる」ものだったのです
Please have a look.
ご覧下さい
Her limbs, which should have been mashed up,
have started to grow back.
すりつぶしたはずの手足も生えてきています
While this is now the ninth time she's been resurrected...
蘇るのは9回目ですが
the only change is that her form becomes
slightly more distorted each time.
少し形が歪になる程度で済んでいます
Mitty...
ミーティ
Mitty, I'm sorry for running away like this.
ミーティ 逃げてごめんな
I won't just let him...
もうあいつの好きになんかさせないから
keep doing as he pleases.
I... I'll figure something out...
オイラが オイラが何とかするんだ
Look, Mitty, it's a bird.
ほら ミーティ 鳥だよ
It's the same one that was screeching
back then, you know.
あの時 鳴いてたのこんな奴だったぞぉ
Not to your liking? Mitty...
だめかい ミーティ
It's no use...
だめだ なんを使っても 苦しむだけ
No matter what I try using, she just suffers.
I'm sorry for forcing you to stay alive for nothing...
無駄に生かしてごめんな
I'll put you out of your misery now.
今楽にしてやるから
I'll search for it...
探すんだ
A way to kill Mitty without making her suffer.
ミーティを苦しませずに 殺せる方法を
There must be one somewhere out there...
どこかにあるはずだ どこかに
Somewhere...
"Sparagmos".
「ズパラグモス」 「枢機へ還す光」
The "light that returns to the cardinal point."
There was a certain Relic that he called that.
あいつが そう呼んでた遺物があってな
One of Mitty's eyes was squashed by it,
and that's the only part of her that doesn't regenerate.
ミーティの固めはそれで潰されて そこだけ戻らねーんだ
Any spot it hits disappears
as if it's completely come undone.
当たった部分が まるでほどけるように消えて
Immediately afterward,
the surrounding air burns up to nothing...
直後に空気が焼き切れる
It's just like the Incinerator!
火葬砲と同じ
If you were to use it... then Mitty...
お前のそれなら ミーティを
H-hold on a minute!
まっ待ってくれ
その ミーティは
Uh...
Has Mitty...
Has Mitty truly lost her humanity?!
ミーティは本当に人間性を失っているのか
She responds to people calling her, and-
呼べば返事だってするし それに
Those are just reflexes.
ただの反応だ
No matter what I tried, real communication
between us proved impossible.
どんな手段でも 意志の疎通はできなかったぜ
But even so... her eye...
なのに あの目だ
I'm sure you've seen it, too...
お前も見たろ
Even now, I have a feeling that Mitty's...
今だにミーティは
that Mitty's soul is imprisoned within that body.
ミーティの魂は あの身体に囚われてる気がするんだ
Please...
少し 考えさせてくれ
give me some time to think.
Hmm... I understand.
そうだよな
N-Nanachi...?
ナ ナナチ
I'm sorry...
悪かったな 急に変なこと頼んじまってよ
I asked you to do something
strange like that outta nowhere.
Don't worry, I'll still keep treating Riko either way.
リコは治レてやるから安心しな
That girl...
あの子は ミーティのお気に入りだしな
Mitty's really taken a liking to her, you know.
I thought of you as being so dependable, but...
あんなにも頼もしく思えた君が
just now you appeared so fragile.
今は ひどく 儚く見える
The vast amount of medicines here...
and the poisons, too...
ここにある夥しい薬も 毒も
all of them are for the purpose
of trying to restore Mitty's dignity.
全てミーティの尊厳を取り戻すための物
それが 君の「生きる理由」なら
If that is your very reason for living...
after I have killed Mitty...
ミーティを殺したあと
what... what will become of you?
君は 君はどうなってしまうんだ
Hey... just how many days
have you been feeling down now?
お前なぁ 何日凹んでんだよ
Let's have a meal.
飯にしようぜ
I'll make ya something really hearty.
栄養たっぷりのを作ってやるぜ
You wanna have some shroom-bear meat?
タケグマの肉にするか
Huh?!
It's gonna be another one of Nanachi's dishes!
またナナチ飯になってしまう
N-Nanachi!
ナっ ナナチ
Let me cook!
僕に作らせてくれ
From what I've seen...
作り方を見るに
Nanachi mixes everything way too much...
ナナチはなんでも混ぜすぎる
I've gotta bring out the best of the ingredients.
素材を生かすんだ
Hey, you really suck at skinning...
お前 皮剥ぐのへたくそだなぁ
Want some help?
手伝おっか
Just go and take a seat!
いいから座っててくれ
The meat is really quite dark...
随分黒い肉なんだな それに臭い
and it stinks, too...
If I remember right, Riko did something like this...
確か リコはこう
Huh?! Were the innards supposed to come first?
内臓が先だったか
Ah! Something ripped off!
何か破れた
これ 洗っておくべきなのか
This here... am I supposed to rinse it first?
Hey, doesn't this smell, like, super bad to you?
おい なんかこれ やべぇ臭いしないか
オイラの作ったより美味しくねぇ
This is worse than the stuff I made!
Gross!
えぐい
The smell of excrement is filling my mouth!
排泄物の臭いが□いっぱいに
Hey, go on and call it irredeemable!
なぁ おい 度し難いって言ってみろよ
It's irredeemable!
度し難い
Before anyone knows it,
the shooting stone leaves a trail,
いつしか 岩つぶては
尾を引く 焼けた鉄の雨となり 氷を鎧う木々を
which falls as red-hot iron rain...
The ice-covered trees
proceed to transform into clouds...
雲へと変えてゆきます
In the gap in the sky,
a large turtle with its neck stretched out is...
狭間の空に 首を伸ばした大きな亀が
"Please kill Mitty for me"...
「ミーティを殺してくれ」
Ever since then, Nanachi hasn't
approached me about it again.
あれ以来 ナナチから持ちかけては来ない
Is it okay to just leave things as they are?
このままでいいのか
Nanachi, allow me to ask just one thing...
ナナチ 一つだけ聞がせてくれ
Is Mitty unhappy being together with you?
ミーティは 君といて不幸なのだろうか
Personally, I really don't think-
僕にはとてもそうは
I know what you're trying to say.
言いたい事はわかるぜ
You're thinking that,
"She seems to be living so peacefully,
あんなに穏やかに生きてるのに
so is it really necessary to kill her," right?
殺す必要があんのかって話だろ
I...
オイラも オイラもそのうちどうにかなって死ぬ
I myself will die somehow or other one of these days.
After that happens...
そしたら ミーティは 永遠に一人ぼっちだ
Mitty will be all alone for eternity.
You know, Mitty never eats and she still doesn't die.
ミーティはさ モノも食わないし死ぬこともない
But if she gets stabbed, it still hurts her...
けど刺されりゃ痛いし
and she even sheds tears.
涙だって流すんだ
Even if those are mere reflexes,
she'd still be forced to continue suffering forever.
それがただの反応だとしても
永遠に苦しみ続けなきゃならねぇ
She's not even capable of screaming out,
and yet her soul would remain imprisoned...
悲鳴すら上げることもできず
魂を囚われたまま 永遠にだ
eternally.
Reg, this is the last chance for us.
レグ これは最後のチャンスなんだ
You can set Mitty free.
ミーティを解放出来る 最後の
Our last.
Please.
お願いだ
An opportunity like this won't ever present itself again.
こんなに都合のいいことは 二度と起こらねえ
I understand.
了解した
Nanachi, promise me this...
ナナチ 約束してくれ
Even if Mitty isn't around anymore,
don't take your own life.
ミーティがいなくなっても
自ら命を絶ったりしないって
しねぇよ
I won't.
I've still gotta take care of Riko... right?
リコを治さなぎゃ だろ
Even after you're done treating Riko!
リコを治した後もだ
Oh...
んなぁ 残酷だなぁ
How cruel...
わかったよ 約束する
I understand. I promise.
In that case... leave it to me.
なら 僕に任せろ
With every ounce of my thoughts and feelings...
ありったけの想いで 送り出してやる
I will send her off.
Alright.
よし
Sorry for making you stick around here
with me all this time.
今まで付き合わせてごめんな
It won't be long before we can meet again.
またすぐ 会えるからな
Reg, I'm counting on you.
レグ 頼む
WAIT!
待って
Mitty!
ミーティ
Mitty, I'm sorry!
ミーティ ごめんよ
I was wrong!
オイラが間違ってた
I'm sorry.
ごめん ほんとにごめん
I'm so, so sorry!
We'll always, always be together, okay?
ずっとずっと一緒だからな
Mitty, you're so warm...
ミーティは 暖かいなぁ
Mitty, thank you...
ミーティ ありがとうな
Reg...
レグ やってくれ
Do it.
ミーティ
Mitty...
お オイラの オイラの たからもの
My...
My... treasure...
C-cut it out!
や やめろう
Come on, this is no time to be feeling down.
さあ落ち込んでる場合じゃないぞ
I...
ぼくは なんで悲しい
Why am I sad?
Hey, you need to eat too, right?
ほら 君も食うだろ
Ah, that smells great.
ああ いい匂いだ
Once you're done eating, we're heading out.
それを食べたら 出発だ
What's that odd smell?
なんだ この異様なにおいは
Hmm...
You're adapting way better than I could've ever imagined!
お前順応性高すぎだろう
Nanachi, you're good at this!
ナナチ上手
Hey, is that alright?
おい これでいいのかな
Well?
おい あぶねって
Hey, that's dangerous!
Reg, good morning.
レグ おはよ
Good morning, Riko.
おはよ リコ
Since she's still recovering, I thought I'd make her
a stew that's nice and easy to eat,
病み上がりだから 食いやすいシチュー作ってやろうとしたら
but she kept finding fault
with the way I was preparing it.
オイラのつくり方にケチつけてくんだよ
So that's what that odd smell was...
異様なにおいの正体はこれか
If you remove the entrails, it's gonna taste bland, right?
持つ取り除いたりしたら 味しないだろ
It'll be fine, just fine.
いいからいいから
I see demonfish also inhabit the fourth layer.
ガンキマスって四層にも棲んでたんだね
That's it. That's the way.
いいよいいよ
Now carefully take it out.
丁寧に取っていってね
Nanachi, you're good with your hands, huh?
ナナチ器用だね いいよいいよ
That's it. Now you've got it.
Hey! Don't just stand there, do something!
おい 見てねーでどかしてくれよ
She's been like this since she first saw me...
コイツオイラみてもハナッからこんなんで
Hey, why you acting like you wanna rub me, too?
何触りたそうにしてんだよ
Nanachi, you don't seem to be hating it
as much as when I did it.
ナナチ 僕の時より 嫌がってない気がする
You...!
おま
お前の触り方がいやらしいからだろ
That's 'cause you rub me in a lewd kinda way, okay?!
Pan-Fried Demonfish
Well...
Th-the bottom line's the taste. The taste, okay?
よ 要は 味だぜ 味
Was it good?
美味しかった
Well... It was alright.
ま まぁ まぁまぁだな
You're not half bad.
やるじゃん
I'm glad to hear that.
よかったぁ
手伝ってくれたおかげだよ
It's thanks to your help!
The eggs are yummy, too.
たまごのも美味しいから食べてみて
Try one.
Wait, wasn't there someone else here, too?
ねぇ もうひとり誰かいなかった
Hm? Hm?
How do you...?
おまえ どうして
Huh? Why did I think that, again?
あれ なんでそう思ったんだっけ
Ah...
Well, you see, I had this terribly frightening dream.
んーっとね 私すごく怖い夢を見ててね
I can't remember it all that well, but...
よくは思い出せないけど
when I came to...
気がついたらね
I found myself inside this pitch-black boulder-like thing
that was horribly heavy and wouldn't budge.
ものすごーく重くて びくともしない
真っ黒な岩みたいなのの中にいてね
At first, there was this cavity inside it
that was about the same size as me...
最初は私と同じ大きさの空洞があったんだけど
but it kept getting smaller and smaller.
それが どんどん狭くなってくの
It was so painful, so agonizing...
痛くて苦しくて
I didn't even understand what I was anymore...
私 自分が何だったかもわからなくなっちゃって
I even forgot how to speak...
言葉の出し方も忘れちゃって 怖くて怖くて
I was scared - so scared - and I just kept crying...
ずっと泣いてたの
Then I heard crying.
But this crying wasn't coming from me.
At first, I was startled...
はじめはびっくりしたけど
but then I realized that the other girl was afraid, too.
その子も怖がっているのが分かって
That helped ease my mind, if just a little.
そしたら少しだけ安心して
Then, you see, I stayed like that for quite a while...
私ね ずっと長い間そうしていたの
怖くなっても 目の前にもっと怖がってる子がいて
Even when I got scared, there was this girl
right in front of me who was surely even more frightened.
I couldn't speak, but with my eyes alone
I kept on telling her, "It'll be alright, it'll be alright..."
声も出せないけど 目だけで大丈夫だよって
ずっと ずっと
Then I smelled something like smoke,
and the crying stopped.
煙みたいな匂いがしてね 鳴き声が止んでたの
You know, that girl simply left
without ever turning to look back...
その子ね 振り向かずにいちゃったんだけど
but I could see her profile.
横顔が見えたの
And she was just like all of the cave raiders I've seen...
私がずっと見てきた探窟家と同じ
That eye I saw was filled with longing.
あこがれに溢れた目
And then, I remembered what it was
I wanted to be one day.
それで 私 目分が何になりたいのか思い出して
I thought, "I need to get going"...
行かなきゃって思って
At the time, I had a feeling I'd see her again.
その時ね 私また あの子に会える気がしたの
And then I woke up.
そしたら目が覚めて
Hm?
Nanachi, Riko once...
ナナチ リコは リコは赤子のころ一度死んで
Riko died once when she was a baby,
and was brought back to life again
by the power of a Relic.
遺物の力で再び命を得てるんだ
Riko's life may very well be deeply tied to the Abyss...
りこの命は もしかしたら アビスと深いところで繫がっていて
Reg... it's alright.
レグ いいんだ
I'm gonna head out for a bit to fetch some water.
ちょっと 水汲んでくるわ
This time, make sure you really protect her.
っ今度はちゃんとお前が守ってやるんだぜ
Riko...
リコ
Hm?
The truth is...
実は
We're here.
ついだぜ
I come to this same place when I'm injured.
オイラも怪我した時はここだ
Wow...
Strange beasts that I've never seen anywhere else
also come here to take a dip.
他じゃ見た事ない不思議な獣も入りに来るんだぜ
You sure this place is alright?
大丈夫なのか
They're docile to the point you can even pat 'em.
撫でちゃえるぐらい大人しいぜ
深いところは 刺激が強いからやめときな
The deep spots can be overly stimulating,
so stay outta 'em.
'Kay.
There's light coming up from below.
下から光が来てる
レグごめんひとりで脱げないから 手伝って
Reg, sorry, but I can't get this off by myself.
Give me a hand.
O-okay...
Riko, lift your arm a bit.
リコ 脇あけて
Hey, Reg, you wanna go in with me?
ねえ レグも一緒に入ろ
I-I'm just gonna keep a lookout, okay?
ぼっ 僕は見張りをするから
Go on and get in...
入ってやりなよ
Sometimes blood-sucking insects
come to have a bite...
たまに羽虫が血吸いに来るからな
and you're pretty good at shooing those away, right?
追っ払うのは得意だろ
I'll take lookout duty myself.
見張りはオイラがやっとくからさ
It's warm!
あったかい
Ah, the bottom seems pretty slippery...
足元結構滑るかも
Be careful.
気をつけて
Whoa!
Wherever we go, the color dissipates around us!
私達入ったとこだけ 色が避けてく
Reg, look, look!
レグ見てみて お湯なのに ちっちゃい魚もいる
Even though the water's hot,
there are small fish in here!
The fish are eating the dead skin that's floating up.
魚が浮いた垢食べてるよ
For some reason... I feel thirsty...
なんか 喉が渇く
痛たた たた
Ouch! O-ow...
Riko?!
I-I...
I-I'm fine...
だ 大丈夫 お湯がしみただけ
The hot water just stung a bit.
Huh?
Hm?
Reg...
レグ
What's up with your penis?
ちんちんどうしたの
Hm?
I don't know!
わからない
This is... This is...
これは これは
irredeemable.
度し難く
Hmm? What's with you two?
お前ら何 まだそんなふわふわした感じだったの
You're really still that fickle about this?
レグ ほら ちゅーまで済ませてただろう
Reg, come on, you've already kissed her, right?
Kissed...
No point in acting embarrassed now.
今更そんな恥ずかしがんなよ
Reg, what's this kiss thing about?
レグ ちゅーってなんのこと
Uh, that was...
いやっそれは
That was hardly a kiss...
決してちゅーではなく
ナナチ 卑怯だぞ
Nanachi, how cowardly! You get in here, too!
君も入れ
What are you talking about?
何言ってのお前
I'm on lookout duty here,
so go ahead and take your time in there.
ちゃんと見張ってるんでごゆっくり
What's this about a kiss?
ちゅーってなんおこと
Hey, come on.
Jeez, I can't bear to watch this...
まったく みてらんえーよ
ミーティ ありがとな
Mitty... thanks.
You pulled Reg's treasure up outta that place...
レグの宝物 引っ張り上げてくれて
A bit longer...
もう少し もう少しだけ待っててくれるかな
I hope you can wait for me just a bit longer...
Riko! Hang in there!
リコ 気をしっかり
あと五個だ
Five more left!
A big central one comes next. Hold her down tight.
でかい芯いくぜ しっかり押さえとけよ
Just the thumb...
親指だけ
Even if it's the thumb alone, at least it moves!
親指だけでも 動く
リコ
Riko.
Reg, what's the matter?
レグ どうしたの
I'm sorry...
すまない僕が下手に切ってしまったばかりに 腕が
Because I did such a bad job making the cut...
your arm is...
Reg, I'm the one who asked you to do it.
レグ 頼んだのは私なのよ
B-but...
で でも
In the end, it was Nanachi who saved you.
結局は ナナチが助けてくれて
Nanachi told me...
ナナチ 言ってたよ
Told me that while you were working to save me, Reg,
you were crying the whole time and were very worried...
レグ 私を助ける間 ずっと泣いてて
一生懸命悩んでたって
I also heard that upon seeing you like that,
Nanachi thought, "That's me right there,"
それ見てたらね 「あれはオイラだ」って
思わず助けに出ちゃったんだって
and rushed to save me without so much as a thought.
レグ この傷は証なの
Reg... this scar is proof.
Precious proof that you protected me, Reg.
レグが私を守ってくれた 大切な証なのよ
Riko...
リコ
Huh?
ナナチ
Nanachi!
どうした
What's wrong?
Well...
Oh, it's nothing...
もう なんでもねーよ
Hey, Nanachi!
ねぇ ナナチ
Hm?
I have something to ask of you.
お願いがあるの
Would you consider coming along with us?
私達と一緒に来てくれないかな
Sure.
いいぜ
Really?!
ほんと
Nanachi, I'm so happy! You're really okay with it?!
ナナチ 嬉しい いいの
Yeah...
Nanachi!
ナナチ
Ah, get off of me!
離れろよ
W-well... Mitty did take a real liking to you.
ま まあ お前はミーティのお気に入りだ
If I abandoned you midway through your journey,
she'd be mad at me next time we meet.
途中で投げ出したら 次会った時怒られちまう
レグだけじゃ頼りねーしな
And you can't rely on just Reg alone, after all.
That's a good point.
ごもっとも
Let's not forget that Riko's cooking
is also really good, right?
リコの料理も美味しいものな
Well...
What? What did you say?
That aside...
そんなことより おいおい話すけどよ
Well, I'll tell you the full story in due time, but...
I came from the place that you're heading for.
おいら お前たちが目指す場所から来たんだ
You mean... the one you mentioned earlier?
それって 例の
I said, "in due time."
「おいおい」だぜ
Well then!
そんじゃ
Let's get started with the preparations.
早速準備するかあ
We've got quite a lot to do.
結構やることあんぞ
Hey, you wanna get going as soon as we can, right?
なぁ 出発は早いほうがいんだろ
Yeah!
うん お母さんが待ってるの
My mother is waiting for me, after all!
Preparation of Preserved Medicines
Sorting of Cave-Raiding Equipment
Procurement of Water-Repellent Materials
Arm Rehabilitation
Construction of a Support
Completion of a New Backpack
Well then, shall we get going?
ほんじゃ行くか
Yeah!
Nanachi!
ナナチ
Oh?
I see her signature has disappeared...
反応が消えてますね
Congratulations, Nanachi...
おめでとう ナナチ ついに成し遂げたんですね
You've finally managed to do it.
I would like to express the extent of my gratitude to you.
あなたにはたくさんのお礼が言いたい
I would very much like to see you again...
是非とも また会いたいですね